# Jarrett D. Phillips, BSc. (Hons.), MBinf., PhD. ABD

☑ jphill01@uoguelph.ca

jphill01
in Jarrett D. Phillips

Jarrett Phillips
 Jarrett Phillips

R<sup>©</sup> Jarrett Phillips

## **Professional Summary of Research Interests and Expertise**

A highly motivated and passionate bioinformatician, data scientist and researcher naturally driven by curiosity to use mathematical, statistical and computational methods to answer fundamental and applied research questions in biodiversity science, evolutionary biology, ecology, genomics and bioinformatics, particularly related to molecular species identification and discovery through DNA barcoding and other DNA-based approaches.

### **Education**

# Doctor of Philosophy (PhD.), Computational Sciences

2016-Present

University of Guelph

- Thesis title: A Novel Statistical Framework for Assessment of Intraspecific Haplotype Sampling Completeness
- Cumulative GPA: 90%

Advisor: Dr. Daniel J. Gillis, School of Computer Science

Co-Advisor: Dr. Robert H. Hanner, Department of Integrative Biology

# An Introduction to Interactive Programming in Python

2014

Rice University

- Online course through Coursera on the development of interactive applications in Python
- Grade received: 98.4%

## Master of Bioinformatics (MBinf.)

2013-2014

University of Guelph

- Primary coursework in bioinformatics, data science, statistics, and machine learning within the R Statistical Computing Environment
- Major research project title: Assessing haplotype sampling efficiency in Actinopterygii using DNA barcodes
- Cumulative GPA: 85.8%

Advisor: Dr. Robert H. Hanner, Department of Integrative Biology

Co-Advisor: Dr. Daniel A. Ashlock, Department of Mathematics and Statistics

## **Introduction to DNA Barcoding**

2013

University of Guelph

- Online course through the Open Learning and Education Support (OpenEd)
- Grade received: 97.0%

# Honors Bachelor of Science (BSc. (Hons.)) Biological Science

2009-2013

University of Guelph

 Primary coursework in bioinformatics, evolutionary biology, ecology, mathematics and statistics

### **Research Experience**

### **Summer Research Assistant**

2016

Algoma University

Antunes Plant and Soil Ecology Lab, Department of Biology Invasive Species Research Institute (ISRI)

- Offered bioinformatics and statistical analysis support in R
- Assisted Principal Investigator and undergraduate thesis student with initial drafting of a manuscript on invasive plant root lesion quantification

Lab Assistant Volunteer 2014-2016

Algoma University

Antunes Plant and Soil Ecology Lab, Department of Biology Invasive Species Research Institute (ISRI)

- Offered bioinformatics and statistical analysis support in R
- Assisted with collaborative and outreach initiatives for the Terrestrial Invasive Plant Species (TIPS) Network Project through drafting communication letters to public and private conservation agencies across Canada and the USA seeking volunteers to collect invasive plant species for root lesion quantification

### **Undergraduate Research Assistant**

2013

University of Guelph

Monteiro Vaccine Discovery Research Group

 Performed various experimental techniques (gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) and Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR)) on bacterial polysaccharide samples for vaccine synthesis and development under the supervision of qualified graduate students

Teaching Experience         Graduate Teaching Assistant (GTA)       2016-2020         University of Guelph       2020         C1S*3130 − System Modelling and Simulation       2020         ~ 30 students · Python       2017         CIS*9190 − Discrete Structures in Computing I       2017         ~ 30 students (* '40 students per section)       2016-2019         CIS*2460 − Modelling of Computer Systems       2016-2019         ~ 60 students · R, Excel, Java       2021         Undergraduate Student Supervision         Navdeep Singh (with Dan Gillis)       2021         University of Guelph       2020-2021         CIS*4900 · HACSim RShiny web application       2020-2021         Scarlett Bootsma (with Dan Gillis)       2020-2021         University of Guelph       2018         CIS*4900/4910 · HACSim simulation study       2018         Steven French (with Dan Gillis)       2018         CIS*4900/4910 · HACSim R package       2017         Assistantships, Awards, Scholarships and Travel Grants         Graduate Teaching Assistantships       2017-2020         University of Guelph       \$34,506.00-35,148.00         Graduate Research Assistantships       2017-2020         University of Guelph       \$3500.00	Curriculum Vitae (CV)	September 2021	Jarrett Phillips
University of Guelph CIS*3130 - System Modelling and Simulation CIS*1910 - Discrete Structures in Computing I	Teaching Experience		
CIS*3130 – System Modelling and Simulation		TA)	2016-2020
CIS*1910 - Discrete Structures in Computing I	CIS*3130 – System Modelling a		2020
CIS*2460 - Modelling of Computer Systems	CIS*1910 – Discrete Structures	in Computing I	2017
Navdeep Singh (with Dan Gillis) 2021 University of Guelph CIS*4900 · HACSim RShiny web application Scarlett Bootsma (with Dan Gillis) 2020-2021 University of Guelph CIS*4900/4910 · HACSim simulation study Steven French (with Dan Gillis) 2018 CIS*4900/4910 · HACSim R package  Assistantships, Awards, Scholarships and Travel Grants  Graduate Teaching Assistantships 2017-2020 University of Guelph \$34,506.00-35,148.00 Graduate Research Assistantships 2017-2019 University of Guelph \$11,000.00 CPES Graduate Dean's Scholarship University of Guelph \$3500.00 CPES Graduate Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship 2016 University of Guelph \$3000.00 Arthur D. Latornell Graduate Travel Grant 2019 University of Guelph \$500.00 SoCS Travel Grant 2019 University of Guelph \$500.00	CIS*2460 – Modelling of Compu	iter Systems	2016-2019
University of Guelph CIS*4900 · HACSim RShiny web application Scarlett Bootsma (with Dan Gillis) University of Guelph CIS*4900/4910 · HACSim simulation study Steven French (with Dan Gillis) CIS*4900/4910 · HACSim R package  Assistantships, Awards, Scholarships and Travel Grants  Graduate Teaching Assistantships University of Guelph Sadyadae Research Assistantships University of Guelph University of Guelph CPES Graduate Dean's Scholarship University of Guelph Sadyadae Dean's Scholarship University of Guelph Sadyadae Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship University of Guelph	Undergraduate Student Superv	<u>ision</u>	
Scarlett Bootsma (with Dan Gillis)  University of Guelph  CIS*4900/4910 · HACSim simulation study  Steven French (with Dan Gillis)  CIS*4900/4910 · HACSim R package  Assistantships, Awards, Scholarships and Travel Grants  Graduate Teaching Assistantships  University of Guelph  Graduate Research Assistantships  University of Guelph  University of Guelph  CPES Graduate Dean's Scholarship  University of Guelph  CPES Graduate Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship  University of Guelph  Satoon.00  CPES Graduate Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship  University of Guelph  Satoon.00  CPES Graduate Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship  University of Guelph  Satoon.00  Arthur D. Latornell Graduate Travel Grant  University of Guelph  School of Guelph  Satoon.00  Academic Service  School of Computer Science (SoCS) Search Committee  University of Guelph	University of Guelph		2021
Steven French (with Dan Gillis) CIS*4900/4910 · HACSim R package  Assistantships, Awards, Scholarships and Travel Grants  Graduate Teaching Assistantships University of Guelph Sad, 506.00-35,148.00 Graduate Research Assistantships University of Guelph S11,000.00 CPES Graduate Dean's Scholarship University of Guelph S3500.00 CPES Graduate Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship University of Guelph S30000.00 Arthur D. Latornell Graduate Travel Grant University of Guelph S500.00 SoCS Travel Grant University of Guelph S500.00 Academic Service  School of Computer Science (SoCS) Search Committee University of Guelph	Scarlett Bootsma (with Dan Gilli University of Guelph	s)	2020-2021
Assistantships, Awards, Scholarships and Travel Grants  Graduate Teaching Assistantships University of Guelph \$34,506.00-35,148.00 Graduate Research Assistantships University of Guelph University of Guelph \$11,000.00 CPES Graduate Dean's Scholarship University of Guelph \$3500.00 CPES Graduate Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship University of Guelph \$30000.00 Arthur D. Latornell Graduate Travel Grant University of Guelph \$500.00 SoCS Travel Grant University of Guelph \$1000.00 Academic Service  School of Computer Science (SoCS) Search Committee University of Guelph	·	tion study	2018
Graduate Teaching Assistantships University of Guelph Graduate Research Assistantships University of Guelph S11,000.00 CPES Graduate Dean's Scholarship University of Guelph S3500.00 CPES Graduate Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship University of Guelph S3500.00 CPES Graduate Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship University of Guelph S30000.00 Arthur D. Latornell Graduate Travel Grant University of Guelph S0CS Travel Grant University of Guelph S500.00 SoCS Travel Grant University of Guelph S500.00 SoCS Travel Grant University of Guelph S2019 University of Guelph S2019 University of Guelph S2019 University of Guelph	CIS*4900/4910 · HACSim R pack	age	
University of Guelph Graduate Research Assistantships University of Guelph University of Guelph CPES Graduate Dean's Scholarship University of Guelph CPES Graduate Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship University of Guelph S3500.00 CPES Graduate Excellence Entrance (GEE) Scholarship University of Guelph S30000.00 Arthur D. Latornell Graduate Travel Grant University of Guelph SoCS Travel Grant University of Guelph SCS Travel Grant University of Guelph School of Computer Science (SoCS) Search Committee University of Guelph	Assistantships, Awards, Scholar	ships and Travel Grants	
University of Guelph	University of Guelph Graduate Research Assistantshi University of Guelph CPES Graduate Dean's Scholars University of Guelph CPES Graduate Excellence Entra University of Guelph Arthur D. Latornell Graduate Tr University of Guelph SoCS Travel Grant University of Guelph	ips hip nnce (GEE) Scholarship	\$34,506.00-35,148.00 2017-2019 \$11,000.00 2017 \$3500.00 2016 \$30000.00 2019 \$500.00 2019
University of Guelph		CS) Search Committee	2019
	University of Guelph	·	2010

School of Computer Science (SoCS) Search Committee

2017-2018

### University of Guelph

• Two-year contractually-limited Assistant Professor position in cybersecurity

### **Academic Peer Review Service**

Molecular Ecology Resources	2019-2020, 2021
Molecular Biology Reports	2020
Methods in Ecology and Evolution	2020

## **Proceedings**

8 <sup>th</sup> International Barcode of Life Conference	2019
NTNU University Museum and Norwegian Biodiversity Information Centre	
7 <sup>th</sup> International Barcode of Life Conference	2017
University of Johannesburg	
6 <sup>th</sup> International Barcode of Life Conference	2015
University of Guelph	

### Skills

# **Programming Languages and IDEs**

 $R \cdot RStudio \cdot TeX \cdot Python \cdot PyCharm$ 

# **Document Preparation, Spreadsheet Applications, Version Control and Continuous Integration**

LaTeX · RMarkdown · Excel · HTML · Git · GitHub · Travis CI

#### Other

R Shiny

### **Software Development**

HACSim (Haplotype Accumulation Curve Simulator) · R package · RShiny web app

- A novel nonparametric stochastic (Monte Carlo) local search optimization method of iteratively generating species' haplotype accumulation curves through extrapolation to assess within-species sampling completeness
- Available for download through the Comprehensive R Archive Network (CRAN) package repository
- Publication in PeerJ Computer Science was one of the top five most viewed papers in the category Optimization Theory and Computation
- Has been downloaded over 12000 times (c. 290 times per month) since being published in May 2019.

## **Refereed Work**

## **Journal Articles**

- 4. D'Ercole, J., Dincă, V., Opler, P.A., Kondla, N.G., Schmidt, C.B., **Phillips, J.D.**, Robbins, R., Burns, J.M., Miller, S.E., Grishin, N., Zakharov, E.V., deWaard, J.R., Ratnasingham, S. and Hebert, P.D.N. (2020). A DNA barcode library for the butterflies of North America. *PeerJ*.
- 3. **Phillips, J.D.**, French, S.H., Hanner, R.H. and Gillis, D.J. (2020). HACSim: An R package to estimate intraspecific sample sizes for genetic diversity assessment using haplotype accumulation curves. *PeerJ Computer Science*, 6(192): 1-37.
- 2. **Phillips, J.D.**, Gillis, D.J. and Hanner, R.H. (2019). Incomplete estimates of genetic diversity within species: Implications for DNA barcoding. *Ecology and Evolution*, 9(5): 2996-3010.
- 1. **Phillips, J.D.**, Gwiazdowski, R.A., Ashlock, D. and Hanner, R. (2015). An exploration of sufficient sampling effort to describe intraspecific DNA barcode haplotype diversity: examples from the ray-finned fishes (Chordata: Actinopterygii). *DNA Barcodes*, 3: 66-73.

## **Conference Proceedings**

- 3. **Phillips, J.D.**, Gillis, D. and Hanner, R. (2019). HACSim: Iterative extrapolation of haplotype accumulation curves for assessment of intraspecific COI DNA barcode sampling completeness Scientific abstracts from the 8th International Barcode of Life Conference, Trondheim, Norway (ed. Torbjørn Ekrem), *Genome*, 62(6): 349-453.
- 2. **Phillips, J.D.**, Gillis, D. and Hanner, R. (2017). Intraspecific sample size estimation for DNA barcoding: Are current sampling levels enough? Scientific abstracts from the 7th International Barcode of Life Conference, Johannesburg, South Africa (ed. M. van der Bank), *Genome*, 60(11): 881-1019.
- 1. **Phillips, J.D.**, Gwiazdowski, R.A., Ashlock, D. and Hanner, R. (2015). An exploration of sufficient sampling effort to describe intraspecific haplotype diversity in the ray-finned fishes (Chordata: Actinopterygii). Scientific abstracts from the 6th International Barcode of Life Conference, Guelph, ON., Canada (ed. S.J. Adamowicz), *Genome*, 58(5): 163-303.

# **Non-Refereed Work**

### **Blog posts**

- 5. **Phillips, J.D.** (2020). Barcode Cracking. Contributed CEPS Research Highlights article (https://www.uoguelph.ca/ceps/news/2020/02/barcode-cracking)
- 4. **Phillips, J.D.** (2020). Protecting Biodiversity Through the Lens of Genetic Diversity. Contributed guest post to the blog of Dr. Daniel Gillis (https://danielgillis.wordpress.com/2020/01/30/protecting-biodiversity-through-the-lens-of-genetic-diversity/).
- 3. **Phillips, J.D.** (2019). IBOL8 and the Midnight Sun. Contributed guest post to the blog of Dr. Daniel Gillis (https://danielgillis.wordpress.com/2019/07/02/reflections-ibol8-and-the-midnight-sun/).

- 2. **Phillips, J.D.** (2017). The Big Five and IBOL7. Contributed guest post to the blog of Dr. Daniel Gillis (https://danielgillis.wordpress.com/2017/12/06/reflections-the-big-five-and-ibol7/).
- 1. **Phillips, J.D.** (2016). Sample size estimation for DNA barcoding: Are current sampling levels enough? Contributed guest post to the DNA Barcoding Blog (http://dna-barcoding.blogspot.com/2016/01/guest-post-sample-size-estimation-for.html).

### **Newsletters**

1. **Phillips, J.D.** (2016). Sample size estimation for DNA barcoding of ray-finned fishes: Are current sampling levels enough? Contributed newsletter article to the Barcode Bulletin, 7(1).

# Accepted

N/A

# **Submitted**

1. Young, R.G., Persram, M., Friesen, O., Chen, A., Yu, J. **Phillips, J.D.** and Hanner, R.H. R you citing your use of the R statistical computing and graphics environment correctly? *Scientific Data*.

### **To Be Submitted**

- 3. **Phillips, J.D.**, Gillis, D.J. and Hanner, R.H. Lack of statistical rigor in DNA barcoding likely invalidates the presence of a true species' barcode gap. *Frontiers in Ecology and Evolution*.
- 2. **Phillips, J.D.**, Bootsma, S.E., Hanner, R.H. and Gillis, D.J. Solving the genetic specimen sample size problem with a local search optimization algorithm.
- 1. Athey, T.B.T., **Phillips, J.D.**, Hanner, R.H. and McNicholas, P.D. VLF: An R package for the analysis of very low frequency variants in DNA sequences.

### References

Dr. Daniel Gillis
Associate Professor
School of Computer Science
University of Guelph
50 Stone Road East
Guelph, ON.
N1G 2W1
dgillis@uoguelph.ca

Dr. Robert Hanner
Full Professor
Department of Integrative Biology
University of Guelph
50 Stone Road East
Guelph, ON.
N1G 2W1
(519) 824-4120 ext. 53479
rhanner@uoguelph.ca

# Dr. Rodger Gwiazdowski

Adjunct Professor
Department of Environmental Conservation
University of Massachusetts Amherst
Amherst, MA, USA
01003
413-320-3755

rgwiazdowsk@umass.edu

Dr. Robert Young
Postdoctoral Research Associate
Department of Integrative Biology
University of Guelph
50 Stone Road East
Guelph, ON.
N1G 2W1
(519) 824-4120
rgyoung6@gmail.com

Owner Advanced BioConsulting, LLC. 139 Spring Street Shrewsbury, MA, USA 01545 (413) 320-3755

rodger.gwiazdowski@gmail.com